Finding Aid for Ali A. Mazrui papers, 1959-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ali A. Mazrui papers 1959-1989
Mazrui, Ali Al Amin.
12 linear feet
2010226 Aa 2
Professional records, manuscripts, correspondence, and subject files of Ali A. Mazrui, professor of political science and of Afroamerican and African studies at the University of Michigan from 1974 to 1989. Includes material prior to his Michigan appointment.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received through the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies in September 2008. (Donor # 10110 )
No further additions to the collections are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ali Al'Amin Mazrui was born on February 24, 1933, in Mombasa, Kenya. He received a B.A. from the University of Manchester, England, in 1960, an M.A. from Columbia University in 1961, and a D.Phil. from Oxford University in 1966.
Mazrui began his academic career in 1966 at Makerere University in Kampala, Uganda, where he became head of the Department of Political Science and Dean of the Faculty of Social Sciences. In 1973 Mazrui was forced to leave Uganda by President Idi Amin, and joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1974 as a professor of political science. He was affiliated with the university's Center for Afroamerican and African Studies (CAAS) and served as director of the center from 1978 to 1981.
In 1989 Mazrui left Michigan for the State University of New York at Binghamton, becoming the Albert Schweitzer Professor in the Humanities and director of the Institute of Global Cultural Studies.
A prolific author, Mazrui wrote or edited more than twenty books and hundreds of scholarly and popular articles. (A current bibliography may be found at http://igcs.binghamton.edu/igcs_site/igcsdirfullcv.htm#publs.) He was a visiting scholar at many institutions, including Cornell University, the University of Papua New Guinea, Harvard University, and the University of Nairobi. He is generally considered to be an leading scholar in the field of African studies and a major African public intellectual, and was the subject of numerous articles and books. In addition to academic positions, Mazrui served as officer of several scholarly associations in his field, as consultant to the World Bank, the United Nations, and other international organizations, and as a member of the board of the American Muslim Council.[1]
Mazrui wrote on numerous topics, including nationality, ethnic conflict, and religion. He suggested that African cultures are affected by three important influences -- Islam, the West, and its own native tradition -- which he terms Africa's "triple heritage." Identifying himself at different times at different points on the ideological spectrum, but generally left of center, Mazrui was critical of the power wielded by Western countries over Africa and other parts of the third world. His Muslim religion was also a frequent theme of his work, and he was critical of Israel's position in the Middle East, and of Western support for Israel.
Outside of the academic world, Mazrui received the most attention for his work as writer and host of a 1986 documentary television series produced jointly by the BBC and PBS entitled "The Africans." Although partially funded by the US government through the National Endowment for the Humanities, the nine-part program was harshly criticized after its presentation in the United States by NEH chair Lynne Cheney for what she described as its anti-Western politics.[2]
Mazrui was highly critical of Salman Rushdie's 1988 novel The Satanic Verses in numerous venues, likening it to Hitler's Mein Kampf in The Michigan Quarterly Review: "Of course Hitler's book was "anti-Jewish" while The Satanic Verses is "anti-Muslim" ...But fundamentally the two books are works of alienation and divisive in intent and in impact."[3] However, Mazrui urged Muslims not to attack Rushdie physically.
Mazrui left the University of Michigan for SUNY Binghamton after a widely reported bidding war that ultimately resulted in a lucrative compensation package for the scholar. Mazrui commented at the time that in addition to the $500,000 SUNY offer, he left Michigan because he was not satisfied with the university's "commitment to Third World studies."4
Mazrui was married twice and is the father of five sons.
-----------------------------------
Notes
1. "Ali Mazrui," en.wikipedia.org, accessed 4/08/09.
2. Deborah Gilbert, "Mazrui not daunted by controversy over series," University of Michigan University Record, 13 Oct 1986.
3. Ali Mazrui, "Is the Satanic Verses a Satanic Novel? Moral Dilemmas of the Rushdie Affair," Michigan Quarterly Review, Summer 1989, p. 364.
4. Connie Leslie, "Let's Buy A Physicist or Two," Newsweek, 12 Feb 1990.
The Ali A. Mazrui Papers include writings by and about Mazrui professional and personal correspondence, and scholarly and teaching materials. The material covers the mid-1960s until Mazrui's departure from Michigan in 1989. Also material on television series "The Africans." The papers are arranged in ten series: Writings by Mazrui; Materials Related to "The Africans" Television Series; Biographical; Subject Files (1979-1989); Correspondence; Teaching Materials; Scholarly Materials; Clippings; Published Materials; and Writings by Others.
Subjects:
Africa--Civilization.; Africa--Economic conditions.; Africans--Study and teaching.; Mazrui, Ali Al Amin.; Uganda--Politics and government.; University of Michigan. Center for Afroamerican and African Studies.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Writings by Mazrui
  The Writings by Mazrui series (5.0 linear feet) consists of drafts, typescripts, and some published versions of scholarly articles, opinion pieces for periodicals and radio broadcasts, and other works. Since a majority of the manuscripts are undated, they are arranged in alphabetical order by title. If available, dates of articles are noted in the box list. The articles included begin with some of his earliest writings from the mid-1960s, well before he arrived at Michigan. Topics covered include African politics and cultural studies, African international relations, and international political relations. Included are scripts for numerous broadcasts on African topics made by Mazrui on the University of Michigan public radio station WUOM in the 1980s.
  - "1976 Southern Africa and Competitive Imperialism,", typescript (Box 1)
  - "Abstract Verse and the African Tradition," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Academic Freedom Versus Authoritarianism in East Africa", typescript (Box 1)
    (written for The Times Higher Education Supplement (London), August/September 1980)
  - "Academic Freedom Versus Blind Social Force in East Africa,", typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and Afghanistan," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and America: The Politics of Culture and the Culture of Politics," conference paper October 1985, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and Democratic Administrations in the US," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and Nuclear Proliferation," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Arab-Israeli Conflict," conference paper July 1979, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Japanese," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Legacy of the Second World War," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Modern World," 1968, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the New 'Polish Question,'" WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the Third World," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the United Nations: The Last Twenty Five Years," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa and the West: New Tools for Old," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa Between Democratic and Republican Administrations: A Note," Africa Report, January-February 1981, typescript and published version (Box 1)
  - "Africa Between Ideology and Technology," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa Between Nationalism and Nationhood," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa Between the Ottoman Empire and the Legacy of Ataturk: Relativism and Universalism in Political Culture," undated, typescript (Box 1)
    (book chapter,)
  - "Africa Discovers Christopher Columbus," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa Entrapped: Between the Protestant Ethic and the Legacy of Westphalia,", typescript and offprint (Box 1)
    (chapter in Hedley Bull and Adam Watson (Eds.) The Expansion of International Society (Oxford: Clarendon Press) pp. 289-308, 1984)
  - "Africa in Micro-Dependency," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa in the 1970s Political Unrest and Cultural Ferment," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa in the World: The African Implications of the Great Depression and World War II," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa in World Affairs,", typescript (Box 1)
    ("lecture delivered at the Program of African Studies, Northwestern University, Spring 1975")
  - "Africa in World Diplomacy," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa on the Eve of Tomorrow: Some Socio-Political Trends," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa, Black History, and the American Dream," February 1987, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa, China and Japan: The Political Ecology of Black-Yellow Relations", typescript (Box 1)
    (based on chapter of 1975 book)
  - "Africa, My Conscience and I," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa: Cultural Liberation and the Future of the Educated Class," conference paper December 1976, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa: From Foreign Rule to Foreign Relations," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa: The Fall and Rise," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa: The Politics of Technological Change," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's 1980 A Selective Retrospect," WUOM radio broadcast, undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Electoral Experience," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Heritage: The Indigenous Personality," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Relevance to Modern Civilization: Past Influences and Future Trends," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Triple Heritage of Play: From God to Gender," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Triple Heritage Revisited: Old and New Confluences of Culture," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Africa's Underdevelopment and the Imperial Experience: The Search for Solutions," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The African Child and a Continent in Crisis,", typescript (Box 1)
    (extracts from keynote address and commentary delivered at UNICEF symposium, Harare, March 1988 and pub. in Africa Events, May 1988)
  - "The African Child: The Lullaby of Death," (TV proposal for UNICEF), typescript (Box 1)
  - "A Continent of Crisis," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The African Condition, (Introduction to the Hebrew Edition, 1984)", typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Democracy as an Endangered Species: In Quest of Conservation," symposium paper October 1983, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Democracy as an Endangered Species: Thoughts on the Nigerian Example," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The African Intellectual and the Challenge of South Africa," lecture July 1971, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Islam and Competitive Religion: Between Revivalism and Expansion," in Third World Quarterly, April 1988, undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Leadership and Conflict of Values," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Liberation from Dedan Kimathi to Fidel Castro," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Oratory in European Languages," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Political Thought," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Radicalism and Arms Control," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Religions in Western Scholarship: Introduction," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African Women in International Diplomacy," WUOM radio broadcast July 28, 1989, typescript (Box 1)
  - "African-Arab Relations in a North-South Perspective," conference paper, February 1982, typescript (Box 1)
    (, also presented under the title "Afro-Arab Relations and the Future of the World: South-South Relations in a North-South Perspective," conference paper, June 1981)
  - "'The Africans': A Response to Mazrui-Bashers," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "'The Africans': Between Bias and Balance?" undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "After Food Aid, Water Aid,", typescript (Box 1)
    ("article commissioned by The Listener (London), June 1986.")
  - "The American Constitution and the Liberal Option in Africa: Myth and Reality," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Amin's Coup: Ethnicity and the Military-Agrarian Complex," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "An African Takeover of the 'British' Commonwealth?" WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Anatomy of Violence in Contemporary Black Africa," January 1976, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Ancient Art of Woodcarving at the Coast -- Is It Dying?" undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Anger and Nationhood," miscellaneous notes undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Angola and Afro-Soviet Relations," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Apartheid and Botha's Bread Basket," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Apolo Milton Obote of Uganda: The Man and the Leader in Politics," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Arabs and the Political Economy of Third World Solidarity: The View from Africa," conference paper October 1979, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Archival Tradition and International Stratification," September 16, 1982, typescript (Box 1)
    (article "based on a lecture delivered at the National Gallery, Harare, Zimbabwe,")
  - "Archives and the (Un)Common Man: Towards An Indigenous Theoretical Framework," conference paper April 1980, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Are Great Orators A Dying Breed in Africa," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Are Intellectuals an International Class? The View from East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Armed Kinsmen and the Origins of the State," (Box 1)
    (reprint from Journal of Asian and African Studies, January-October 1977)
  - "Bad Neighbour Policies in Southern Africa and the Middle East," WUOM radio broadcast February 4, 1981, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Baganda and the Japanese: Comparative Response to Modernization," undated, and lecture, "The Japanese and the Baganda," August 1970, typescripts (Box 1)
  - "The Barrel of the Gun and the Barrel of Oil," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Barren Soil," The UNESCO Courier, August-September 1982 (Box 1)
  - BBC Reith Lectures 4-6, reprinted in The Listener, November-December 1979 (Box 1)
  - "Before Idi Amin: Ideology and Religion in the First Republic of Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 1)
    (with appendix dated April 1979)
  - "Believers and Unbelievers in Southern African Politics," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Between Development and Decay," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Between Partition and Petroleum: Islamic Resurgence in Territorial and Energy Perspectives," conference paper August-September 1980, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Between Science and Society: The Social Responsibility of Scholarship," conference paper November 1984, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Between Sex and Science: Africa's Twin Revolutions of the 21st Century," background paper for conference November 1987, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Between the Barracks and State House,", typescript (Box 1)
    (draft of article "commissioned by the International Herald Tribune" summer 1984)
  - "Beyond Dependency: Five Strategies of Decolonization," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Billy Dudley and I," reprint from Alternatives 1981 (Box 1)
  - "A Birthday Message: Voice of America and I," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Black Africa and the Politics of Arab Oil," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Black Capitalism and Race Relations in East Africa and the United States," (Box 1)
    (reprint from Afro-American Studies, 1970)
  - "Black Humiliation and Jewish Martyrdom," 1979 BBC Reith lecture, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Black Metaphor and the Racial Boundaries of the English Language," undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - "Black Vigilantism in Cultural Transition: Violence and Viability in Tropical Africa," book chapter 1975, typescript (Box 1)
  - "The Bolsheviks and the Bantu: From the October Revolution to the Angolan Civil War," conference paper April 1976, typescript (Box 1)
  - Book Review of DeGregori Technology and the Economic Development of the Tropical African Frontier and Goody, Technology, Tradition and the State in Africa, undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - Book review of Denis Hills Man With A Lobelia Flute: A New View of East Africa, undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - Book review of Lefever Spear and Scepter and Lee, African Armies and Civil Order, undated, typescript (Box 1)
  - Book review of Mamdani and Shivji undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - Book review of Nyerere Freedom and Socialism, undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - Book Review of Rosberg and Nottingham The Myth of 'Mau Mau,', undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Borrowed Theory and Original Practice in African Politics," 1968, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Boxer Muhammad Ali and Soldier Idi Amin as International Political Symbols: The Bioeconomics of Sport and War," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Branches: An African Saga," undated, typescript (TV proposal) (Box 2)
  - "The British Press and Anglo-African Relations," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Building Socialism Without A Vanguard Party: A Crippled Crusade Against Corruption,", typescript (Box 2)
    (of article "partly based on a public lecture given ... February 1984")
  - "The Caribbean Impact on Africa: Is the Tail Still Wagging the Dog?" conference paper May 1977, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Chained to a Name: An African Perspective", February 1989, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Changing Role of African Intellectuals," presented at public debate in Kampala, February 1969, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Changing Role of African Women," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Changing the Guards from Hindus to Muslims: Collective Third World Security in a Cultural Perspective" (Box 2)
    (reprinted from International Affairs, Winter 1980-81 (and earlier conference paper version))
  - "The Chinese Model and the Soviet Model in Eastern and Southern Africa," Mazrui and Rovan G. Locke undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Christian Power and Muslim Challenge in Africa's Experience," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Church, State and Market-Place in the Spread of Kiswahili: The Political Economy of a Language," Mazrui and Pio Zirimu, conference paper, February 1975, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Civic Violence and Political Violence in Uganda and the United States," conference paper September 1970, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Coleman's Dilemma and I," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Collective Martyrdom in Modern History: From the Mandingo to the Mandelas," conference paper July 1988, typescript (Box 2)
    (and pub. in Caribbean Commentary, February-March 1990)
  - "Colonel Sir Edward Mutesa and General Idi Amin: Two Soldier-Presidents and Two Senses of Democracy," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Columbus Discovers Africa," in Compendium (Columbia University student magazine), 1961 (Box 2)
  - "The Common Man's Charter and the Three Faces of Socialism,", typescript (Box 2)
    (based on lecture given November 1969)
  - "The Commonwealth and the Defence of the Indian Ocean," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Comparative Assassination," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Comparative Conclusions," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Comparing Revolutions: Is Ethiopia the Iran of Africa?" WUOM radio broadcast February 25, 1981, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Computer Culture and New Technocracy: Towards Redefining Development in Africa," conference paper August 1978, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Conflict Resolution and Social Justice in the Africa of Tomorrow: In Search of New Institutions," symposium paper January 1981, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Conservative Tradition in African Thought," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Conspiracy at Makerere," Africa Events May 1987, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Contemporary Case for Violence," written for Institute for Strategic Studies Conference September 1971, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Contradictions of Africa's Decolonization," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Contrasting Revolutions: Ethiopia is Not Iran!" WUOM radio broadcast March 4, 1981, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Conversations with Apolo Milton Obote of Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Counterpenetration and the Education of Western Opinion,", typescript (Box 2)
    ("written and compiled for Africa Events, November/December 1988")
  - "Creative Eclecticism as an Ideological Alternative," written for Alternatives undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Crisis in Independent Uganda," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Crisis of Racial Betrayal: Lessons from Shaka, Shakespeare and Puccini," 1979 BBC Reith lecture, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Cuba and Africa's Nonalignment," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Cultural Aspects of Foreign Aid," ODI Review 2, 1978 (Box 2)
  - "Cultural Engineering and Historical Identity," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Cultural Fate of African Legislatures: Rise, Decline and Prospects for Revival," in Presence Africaine, 1979 and conference paper, August 1976, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Cultural Forces in African Politics: In Search of a Synthesis," conference paper May 1982, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Cultural Forces in World Politics," book proposal undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Cultural Meaning of the Twentieth Century," undated, typescript (Box 2)
    (book and conference proposal,)
  - "Culture and Identity: Primitivism Versus Gloriana," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Culture, Power and Transformation in the Twentieth Century," prospectus undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Culture, Structure and the Ballot Box: A Re-Examination of Africa's Parliamentary Experience," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "'Culture': Is It A Culturally Relative Concept?" undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - 'The De-Anglicization of the Caribbean: Myth or Reality?" October 1989, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Death and My First Novel," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Decolonization: The Political Culture of Resistance," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Dependency: Macro, Micro and Marxist," conference paper November-December 1978, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Development of Lugardism and Its Varied Implications for Present-Day Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Dilemmas of African Historiography and the Philosophy of the UNESCO General History of Africa," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Divinity and Political Mobilization: The Religious Factor in Uganda's Evolution Toward Socialism," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Domestic Modernization and the International Society: Africa Between the Meiji Restoration and the Legacy of Ataturk,", typescript (Box 2)
    (rev. of conference paper, May 1981)
  - "The Dual Polity and the Plural Society in Uganda: Implications for Democracy," Mazrui and Omari H. Kokole, conference paper, December 1985, typescript (Box 2)
  - "The Dual Vanguard of the Black World in the Twenty-First Century," lecture October 1987, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Dual Zimbabwe: Toward Averting Political Schizophrenia," undated, typescript (Box 2)
  - "East Africa in the Stream of African Thought," March 1969, typescript (Box 2)
  - "East Africa in World Affairs: From 'Pax Britannica' to 'Pax Tanzaniana,'" lecture December 1979, typescript (Box 2)
  - "Eastern Africa and American Strategic Planning," WUOM radio broadcast undated, typescript (Box 2)